Department of Political Science Records UA099
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Political Science Records
1947 -- 2002
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Political Science
Robbins, Robert R.
UA099
1.45 Linear Feet 2 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Chairman Robert R. Robbins subject files; and Unprocessed accessions.
Biographical / Historical
The Department of Political Science was one of the original Departments of Instruction created for the academic year 1893-1894. President Capen was the sole instructor that year. The department's curriculum consisted of three subjects. Political Economy, Ancient Law and Roman Law, and International Law constituted the courses from which the major was devised. Additionally, a separate category termed "special work in problems of Government for students electing Political Science as a major subject" was offered additionally. By the 1902-1903 academic year, the Department of Political Science does not appear in the list of Departments of Instruction. Instead the Department has been split into two discreet departments. These were the Department of Public Law and Administration and the Department of Economics and Sociology. By the 1903-1904 academic year, the Department of Political Science once again appears in the list of Departments of Instruction. In that academic year, The Department of Political Science articulates its chief goal as follows, "to give a general view of the most important branches of political economy, beginning with the elements of the science and passing by degrees to work of the investigative order". By the 1924-1925 academic year the Department of Government and International Law and the Department of Economics and Sociology had replaced the Department of Political Science. By the 1939-1940 academic year, the Department of Government and International Law had become the sole successor to the Department of Political Science. The Department of Government and International Law articulated its mission as follows, "The Department of Government concerns itself with the history and development of the forms of organization of political society. Stress is laid upon the structure and actual operation of government."
The Department of Economics and Sociology had dissolved to create two autonomous academic departments - The Department of Economics and the Department of Sociology by the 1939-1940 academic year. These newly created departments no longer served to address the socio-economic course components of the originally created Department of Political Science.
The Department of Government and International Law had become the Department of Government before the beginning of the 1946-1947 academic year. By the 1965-1966 academic year, the Department of Government was renamed as the Department of Political Science. While the mission and essential goals of the Department of Political Science were largely the same as those of its preceding department, these goals were phrased in a slightly different fashion. The mission statement for the Department of Political Science for the 1965-1966 academic year reads, "The Department of Political Science is concerned with the functions and theory of the state, the structure and operation of government, and the nature and development of local, national, and international politics."
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are lised in the detailed contents list.
Scope and Contents
This collection contain subject files created by department chair, Robert R. Robbins; a program for a John Richard Skuse Chair event; and a handbook for public policy and citizen participation.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs
- Chairman Robert R. Robbins Papers, Subject Files, 1947 -- 1970; 1957 -- 1965; UA099.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains subject files, office records, committee papers, teaching documents, personal papers, correspondence, and student information from Chairman Robert R. Robbins. This series includes materials from the time Robbins served as department chair (1957-1969) and 1970 when he still was a professor in the department. In addition, files include some materials from his years at the U.S. Department of State. Many files relate to the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy where Robbins was on the faculty.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically, then chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  75 years from the date of creation.
  - Academic Appointments, 1951 -- 1957; UA099.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Acknowledge, 1958 -- 1959; UA099.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Active Teaching Candidates, 1958 -- 1962; UA099.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Committee re Constitutional Convention, 1960 -- 1961; UA099.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - L'Annee Prochaine [Next Year] [Fletcher School], 1962 -- 1964; UA099.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Anton, Thomas J., 1959 -- 1961; UA099.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Assistantships, 1962 -- 1964; UA099.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Buildings and Grounds, 1960; UA099.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Carbon, 1962; UA099.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Study, 1956 -- 1958; UA099.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Citizenship Clearing House, 1954 -- 1956; UA099.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Committee for Consitutional Reform, 1962; UA099.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Committee - Faculty Personnel, 1958 -- 1962; UA099.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Foreign Relations/RRR, 1957 -- 1964; UA099.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Innovation and Experiment, 1962; UA099.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Comparative Departmental Statistics, 1961 -- 1962; UA099.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - Department - P. Committee, 1966 -- 1968; UA099.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - Faculty - Curriculum (Confidential), 1963; UA099.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Meeting, 1961; UA099.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - Film Rental, 1955 -- 1965; UA099.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher Assistants, 1961 -- 1962; UA099.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher School, 1957 -- 1959; UA099.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher School, 1958 -- 1962; UA099.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher School, 1958 -- 1962; UA099.001.001.00024 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher School, 1961 -- 1962; UA099.001.001.00025 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher School, 1962 -- 1965; UA099.001.001.00026 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher School, 1964 -- 1965; UA099.001.001.00027 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher School, Politics 12b, 1959 -- 1962; UA099.001.001.00028 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher School, Student Enrollment Information, 1961; UA099.001.001.00029 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher School, Teaching Appointments, 1959 -- 1961; UA099.001.001.00030 (Box 1)
  - Foundations, 1963 -- 1965; UA099.001.001.00031 (Box 1)
  - Government - Courses, Fall 1957, Spring 1958, 1957 -- 1958; UA099.001.001.00032 (Box 1)
  - Government (Dept. 1), Family Meetings, Calalozes, 1962 -- 1963; UA099.001.001.00033 (Box 1)
  - Government - Paper Requirements, Enrollment in Courses, 1947 -- 1957; UA099.001.001.00034 (Box 1)
  - Government I Exam, 1962; UA099.001.001.00035 (Box 1)
  - Government I, 1964 -- 1965; UA099.001.001.00036 (Box 1)
  - Government I, Spring, 1965; UA099.001.001.00037 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Program, 1970; UA099.001.001.00038 (Box 1)
  - Graduate School - Fletcher Issue, 1962 -- 1963; UA099.001.001.00039 (Box 1)
  - Graduate School - Flyers, 1961 -- 1963; UA099.001.001.00040 (Box 1)
  - Grant Program, 1962; UA099.001.001.00041 (Box 1)
  - Independent Study Program, 1961; UA099.001.001.00042 (Box 1)
  - James, Roy E., 1962; UA099.001.001.00043 (Box 1)
  - Lambrie Aemos, 1961; UA099.001.001.00044 (Box 1)
  - Memorial to Alfred Church Lane, 1953; UA099.001.001.00045 (Box 1)
  - Photograph: Powers, Vanderhoof, Robbins, 1960; UA099.001.001.00046 (Box 1)
  - Placement Exams, 1962; UA099.001.001.00047 (Box 1)
  - Political Systems, 1955 -- 1965; UA099.001.001.00048 (Box 1)
  - Politics 12b - Fletcher School, 1958; UA099.001.001.00049 (Box 1)
  - Possibilities, 1959 -- 1962; UA099.001.001.00050 (Box 1)
  - Pre-Legal, 1959 -- 1961; UA099.001.001.00051 (Box 1)
  - Robbins, 1962 -- 1963; UA099.001.001.00052 (Box 1)
  - Robbins, RR, Personal, 1957 -- 1964; UA099.001.001.00053 (Box 1)
  - Seminar - Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands, 1964; UA099.001.001.00054 (Box 1)
  - Sociology, 1957 -- 1958; UA099.001.001.00055 (Box 1)
  - Spencer, Henry R., 1950 -- 1956; UA099.001.001.00056 (Box 1)
  - Stanleyville - Department of State Releases, 1964; UA099.001.001.00057 (Box 1)
  - Summer School, 1954 -- 1959; UA099.001.001.00058 (Box 1)
  - Survey of Current Departmental Programs, 1956; UA099.001.001.00059 (Box 1)
  - Teaching Loads, 1961; UA099.001.001.00060 (Box 1)
  - Tenure Review, 1955 -- 1965; UA099.001.001.00061 (Box 1)
  - Travelli Grant, 1961 -- 1962; UA099.001.001.00062 (Box 1)
  - TTPI Seminar Papers, 1964; UA099.001.001.00063 (Box 1)
  - Zimmerman, Professor, Worcester Polytechnic Institute, 1961; UA099.001.001.00064 (Box 1)
- Additional accessions, 1985 -- 2002; UA099.002
  - Program to the John Richard Skuse Chair and handbook for public policy and citizen participation, 1985 -- 2002; UA099-001; .25 Linear Feet (Box 1)
    Open for research.